<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Designing Intelligent Design]]></title>
  <link href="http://extrabiomes.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://extrabiomes.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-23T14:47:17-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://extrabiomes.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[ScottKillen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Terrain Generation]]></title>
    <link href="http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/23/terrain-generation/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-23T13:46:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/23/terrain-generation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may have seen my post on twitter of mountainous terrain generated high above the clouds. Here is how it was done: <!-- more --></p>

<p>Well, before that, let&#8217;s take a look at the image itself:</p>

<p><img src="http://extrabiomes.net/images/screens/TerrainGeneration/1.png" alt="terrain gen" /></p>

<p>Notice that we are standing at y=137 and terrain is towering over us above the clouds. The screenshot was generated by spawning a new world and snapping the shot.</p>

<p>&#8220;But wait, Minecraft doesn&#8217;t generate terrain above y=127,&#8221; you may say. You&#8217;d be right. What you are looking at is terrain generated by a complete terrain generator replacement.</p>

<p>Several days ago, my friend <a href="https://github.com/ExtrabiomesXL/ExtrabiomesXL/issues/225">MineCrak told me</a> about the <a href="http://dev.bukkit.org/server-mods/terrain-control/">TerrainControl</a> bukkit plugin cum forge mod. I finally got around to investigating it and knew it was the ideal solution for the ExtrabiomesXL. I spoke to Khoorn, the mod maintainer, to confirm the licensing. His reply: &#8220;Yes, TerrainControl is completely free.  So you may use it as you want,&#8221; had me hopping around the house with extra Christmas spirit. This is the power of opensource software!</p>

<p>The TerrainControl team has done an amazing job producing the mod. The code is very nicely written and documented and is designed to be modular. I spent a few hours repackaging TerrainControl so that I could make changes and everything would still work if someone also installed TerrainControl itself alongside ExtrabiomesXL.</p>

<p>TerrainControl contains more features than I can list. The TerrainControl wiki lists some <a href="https://github.com/Wickth/TerrainControl/wiki/Features">here</a>. In addition, TerrainControl has a feature requested by many ExtrabiomesXL players: terrain generation parameters are saved <em>by world</em>.</p>

<h2>Impact on ExtrabiomesXL 4</h2>

<p>The integration of TerrainControl means a shortening of the development timetable for ExtrabiomesXL 4. Instead of writing a terrain generator from scratch (which would&#8217;ve been my first) I can focus on tweaking this polish generator and adding the content you have all been wanting.</p>

<p>I can&#8217;t wait.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/21/design-goals/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-21T21:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/21/design-goals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lots of people have asked what is coming in the next version. This time, we get into the design goals for ExtrabiomesXL 4. <!-- more --></p>

<p>When I begin a software project, I like to layout my goals. I list everything I want to do, understanding that it <em>will change</em> because of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_management_triangle">Project Management Triangle</a>. The PMT summed up is &#8220;Pick two: Fast, Good, Cheap.&#8221; Because of the interplay of these three attributes, project design is constant compromise.</p>

<p>Here is our list for the next version of ExtrabiomesXL:</p>

<ul>
<li>Rather than override vanilla terrain generation, we need to have a selectable world type, in the same way that players can select &#8220;Large Biome&#8221; or &#8220;Flat&#8221; worlds.</li>
<li>Expand terrain gen into the full 256 block height along the y-axis. Currently vanilla generation takes place in the lower 128 blocks.</li>
<li>Change the use of biomes: Currently vanilla biomes determine a lot of things, including climate, terrain altitude and flora (plants and trees). This is fine for vanilla, with only a few types of flora, but we are going to expand the number of floral species. Extrabiomes should not determine flora.</li>
<li>Add extremely rare biomes (e.g. enchanted groves, wasteland, extreme mountains, glaciers).</li>
<li>Increase the number of floral species. Nightshade_Proleath bequeathed the <a href="http://www.minecraftforum.net/topic/1519278-">Forgotten Nature</a> mod to us, which includes many, many floral species.</li>
<li>Create a grove layer, which will overlay the biome layer in terrain generation to shape forests so that they transcend the boundaries of biomes. This will allow experience such as finding a jungle in the lowlands and watching the plants and trees change as you move through different climates and altitudes. Also, within forests, scarce groves with mostly one type of tree can be found. This improves the exploration experience.</li>
<li>Add blocks to support the above. All blocks have a use which is added via technology tree or integration with other mods. This provides the motivation for exploration.</li>
<li>Add a simple API, that does not require inclusion in another mod or hard dependencies of any kind.</li>
<li>Integrate with other mods, with priority given to <a href="http://www.feed-the-beast.com/">FTB</a> mods, via published APIs, while avoiding inclusion of APIs and without hard dpendencies.</li>
<li>Include more rock types and generate <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stratum">stratum</a>.</li>
<li>Improve textures.</li>
</ul>


<p>This is our starting list. It is ambitious and long; however, the secret to good design is to shoot for the stars and accept the Sun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beginning Your Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/17/beginning-your-project/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-17T19:16:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/17/beginning-your-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Minecraft was written in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_(programming_language)">Java programming language</a> so your mod is also going to be written in Java. This has certain implications for your work:  <!-- more --></p>

<p>Actually&#8230;<a href="https://twitter.com/minecraftcpw/status/280891535149654016">Java isn&#8217;t <em>mandatory</em></a>, but since we are keeping to the basics (and because ExtrabiomesXL is Java) we will assume it is for this post.</p>

<p>First, of course, you are going to have to know Java. The good news is that it is not difficult to gain a working knowledge of Java. The bad news is that Java is difficult to master. In addition to learning the Java programming language, I highly recommend reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321356683/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0321356683&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=killentime-20">Effective Java</a> by Joshua Bloch.</p>

<p>Second, while it is possible to develop in Java using a text editor, I find an Integrated Development Environment (IDE) is an invaluable tool. I use <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/downloads/moreinfo/java.php">Eclipse</a> because it is (1) <em>free</em>, (2) supported by Minecraft Coder Pack (MCP) and (3) contains very powerful features.</p>

<h2>Using Eclipse</h2>

<p>Setting up your project in Eclipse is simple: Open the MCP Eclipse project (found at forge/mcp/eclipse) and then add the source and resource directories (created <a href="http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/13/organization-and-revision-control/">last time</a>) to the buildpath. (I won&#8217;t tell you how to do it&#8230;you&#8217;ve got to get familiar with Eclipse!)</p>

<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>If everything is set up properly, you will be able to play minecraft from the Eclipse &#8216;Run&#8217; menu.</p>

<p>This will be the last of the basic &#8220;How-To&#8221; style posts. Beginning next time, we will be discussing the specifics of ExtrabiomesXL 4 design.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Organization and Revision Control]]></title>
    <link href="http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/13/organization-and-revision-control/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-13T23:37:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/13/organization-and-revision-control</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For any complex project, organization is very important. Having a way to get yourself out of a mess can also come in handy. This time we discuss how to set up your code and stay organized, and how to control revisions of your work.  <!-- more --></p>

<p>Your project should be organized in a way that facilitates its goals. For ExtrabiomesXL 4, the pertinent philosophies are:</p>

<ol>
<li>Mod code should be separate from protected Mojang code.</li>
<li>Mod code should be separate from Minecraft Forge API code.</li>
<li>Simplification is desirable.</li>
<li>ExtrabiomesXL is a collaborative project. Its organization should not be an obstacle to others.</li>
<li>Resources, e.g. artwork, non code config files, should be readily accessible and identifiable.</li>
<li>All mod files should be located under one central (root) folder to make revision control easier. <em>More on this later.</em></li>
</ol>


<p>As it happens, it is fairly easy to satify all of these philosphies in our project organization. We&#8217;ll get to that in a moment. For now, lets pause and discuss revision control&#8230;</p>

<h2>Revision Control</h2>

<p>Writing software can be a daunting task. Many times you work on something for hours only to find out it doesn&#8217;t work the way you thought it should. When this happens, you may find yourself scratching your head wondering how to get things back to the way that they were. Enter revision control&#8230;</p>

<p>Revision control, also known as version control or source code control, is the management of changes to collections of information. Specifically, revision control software provides an easy way for you to keep track of the changes that happen to your project as you work toward completing it.</p>

<p>To keep it simple, we won&#8217;t get into every aspect of revision control or revision control software. It is enough to say that ExtrabiomesXL is a social open-source project. <code>git</code> is a stable modern full-featured <em>free</em> revision control system, contains many advanced features, and is supported by <a href="http://github.com">github.com</a>, a popular <em>free</em> social coding site. <code>git</code> fits the bill nicely.</p>

<p>Whatever system you use, you should put in the effort to know as much as you can about it. Knowledge of the revision control system can make every difference in a tight spot.</p>

<h2>Revision Control Procedures</h2>

<p>Related to and just as important as project organization is revision control procedures. Strict adherance to revision control procedures directly affects project organization and can help all of your related goals. Likewise, failing to be disciplined with regard to revision control can work to counteract every positive effort in a project. Carefully choose a set of procedures that fits your goals while remaining something you can live with.</p>

<p>For ExtrabiomesXL 4, we want to use revision control to accomplish the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Maintain an official copy of the code, offering hotfixes for bugs requiring immediate attention.</li>
<li>Maintain a development copy of the code for current in-process work and beta testing.</li>
<li>Maintain separate copies of the code for in proces features that we can keep or throw away depending on the success of our work.</li>
</ul>


<p>Above, each &#8220;copy of the code&#8221; is called a <em>branch</em>. The github repository for ExtrabiomesXL 4 will contain two permanent branches: master and devel. (Actually the github repository will contain four permanent branches. The other two have to do with hosting this web site.) We can also create temporary branches as needed for work in progress and merge them into one of the two permanent branches when work is successfuly completed. <code>git</code> allows us to freely switch between branches within the same folder structure of our project.</p>

<p>For those of you wanting to become familiar with <code>git</code> I hightly recommend the <a href="http://git-scm.com/documentation">reference manual</a>. For those wanting to set up revision control procedures, Benjamin Sandofsky wrote a great article, <a href="http://sandofsky.com/blog/git-workflow.html">&#8220;Understanding the Git Workflow&#8221;</a>.</p>

<h2>Return to Organization</h2>

<p>Now that we understand more about the mechanisms involved in keeping our project organized, we can organize our project. As I mentioned, it turns out that there is a simple way to accomplish our goals for this project: Create a folder next to the &#8220;forge&#8221; folder we made <a href="http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/10/getting-started-with-minecraft-forge/">last time</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://extrabiomes.net/images/screens/Organization/1.png" alt="forge folder" /></p>

<p>This solves almost all of our goals stated at the top, except for #5. We can satisfy #5 by navigating into our newest folder and creating a &#8216;src&#8217; folder and any number of other folders to complete the organization of our project.</p>

<h1>Final Thoughts</h1>

<p>I realize that this was a long dry article and reading some of the linked resources about revision control is the definition of tedium. But, trust me on this: <em>All of your efforts will be worth it because big projects (like your future popular Minecraft mod!) live and die by their organization and revision control systems.</em> <strong>Make the investment.</strong></p>

<p>I realize I haven&#8217;t covered the details about how to get your code into a revision control system. The reasons for that are two-fold:</p>

<ol>
<li>It is super easy.</li>
<li>If I tell you how to do it and you don&#8217;t read, it will spoil it for you.</li>
</ol>


<p>Besides: you need to pick the system that fits <em>your</em> goals. There is no right choice and if I give you everything, I&#8217;m implying &#8220;one size fits all.&#8221; It doesn&#8217;t.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started with Minecraft Forge]]></title>
    <link href="http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/10/getting-started-with-minecraft-forge/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-10T22:50:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/10/getting-started-with-minecraft-forge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Setting up the mod development environment used to be a complicated set of steps, but with recent developments in Minecraft Forge, it has become very easy. <!-- more --></p>

<p>Here are the steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Create a folder for your project.</li>
<li>Go to <a href="http://files.minecraftforge.net/">http://files.minecraftforge.net/</a> and download the latest Forge source (the &#8220;src&#8221; link).</li>
<li><p>Open the .zip file you downloaded and put the <em>forge</em> directory into the project folder you created, like so:</p>

<p> <img src="http://extrabiomes.net/images/screens/GettingStarted/1.png" alt="forge folder" /></p></li>
<li><p>Enter the forge folder.</p></li>
<li>Run <code>install.cmd</code> in Windows or <code>install.sh</code> in Linux/MacOS</li>
</ol>


<p>At this point, Minecraft Forge will take over, downloading everything it needs to decompile Minecraft and set up a development environment.</p>

<p><strong>IMPORTANT UPDATE:</strong> There is currently (Forge build #436) a bug in the Forge install script that causes the eclipse project not to be set up properly. The Forge team knows of the bug and is fixing it. For now this install procedure will not work. Stay tuned here for updates.</p>

<p><strong>IMPORTANT UPDATE #2:</strong> I just tried this with the <a href="http://files.minecraftforge.net/">latest Forge</a> (build #445) and it works like a charm.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In the beginning...]]></title>
    <link href="http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/09/in-the-beginning-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-09T19:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://extrabiomes.net/blog/2012/12/09/in-the-beginning-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I develop the <a href="http://www.minecraftforum.net/topic/1090288-">ExtrabiomesXL</a> mod for Minecraft. Recently, I realized that to make the mod what it should be, it needed to be rewritten. I created this blog to help you follow along in the process.</p>

<p>I have created a <a href="https://github.com/ScottKillen/ebxl4">repository</a> for the project on <a href="http://github.com">github.com</a>. The code is open source and the idea is that you can clone or fork the project and follow along here. Most modding is not difficult, but it can be complicated. It is my hope that this blog will help you to understand how mods work and, if you&#8217;re into such things, how to write a mod of your own.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
